Okay, welcome back, discrete optimization,
knapsack.
So I want to go back to the branch and
bound, and talk a little bit about search
strategies.
I put something under the rug, and I
want to cover them during this lecture.
And you're going to see, some of these
things
are going to be very interesting later on,
okay?
But you need, you need to understand them.
It's going to build on branch and bound,
but just refine the kinds of thing,
actually expand the kinds of things that
you can do in branch and bound.
Okay?
Remember, branch and one we are working
with real artifacts that we can break but
still we are using the linear relaxation
in general,
or relaxation in general to actually
compute good, you
know, optimistic episodes of the best you
can do.
Okay?
So once again the key idea between branch
and bound is that you look at
this exhaustive search, and you want to
explore a very tiny piece of this tree.
Okay?
And you do that with basic, you know,
relaxation ID.
Okay?
Now one
of the things I didn't talk about last
time is
that you can search that tree in many
different ways.
So, we saw that first branch and bound and
I will talk about a little bit
about it again such that to refresh your
memory, but there are other things you can
do.
And some of them are, you know, code best,
you know, best, best search, best-first
search or, you know, limited discrepancy
search,
and that's what I want to cover today.
Okay I want to give you an idea that, you
know, there
is one thing that you need to consider
when you solve a problem.
It's also
how you explore that, that particular,
that particular trait.
There are many others, and you will see
more in this class, okay?
But at this point, I just want to give you
some of
the ideas on what you can do, and compare
them, okay?
So that first search, you explore your,
your,
your, no, that's what we saw last time.
You explore your tree in a tree in that
first fashion,
and you prune the search tree as soon as
you come
back to a node, and that node is an
optimistic evaluation
which is worse than the best solutions you
have found, okay?
That's depth-first search,
okay?
Now we going to see best-first search.
And the key idea there is that you want to
select at any stage the node which has the
best evaluation.
Okay.
So that's what best-first is.
And we'll see a limited discrepency search
where
what you will do is trusting a greedy
heuristic.
And you'll be, be following these
heuristic and then allowing you
to move away from the heuristic in a very
systematic fashion.
So I'll go into the details of these two
things, okay?
So let, you know I just want to remind you
of that first search first, okay?
And we are using the good eval-, the
linear relaxation here for the knapsack
problem, okay?
And remember what we did was basically
exploring these tree, we
would find a good solution there, with a
cost of 80.
And then we would go back to the other
part
of the tree here, where we're done selling
the first item.
And you see that the optimistic evaluation
here is worse than
the best solution that we have found, and
therefore you can
prove this entire tree.
Okay so that's what I told you before, in
that first
search, when you have an optimistic
evaluation of a note, you compare
it to the best solutions that you have
found so far,
and if it's worse then you just throw the
entire sub-tree away.
Okay?
So that's what that first search is about.
So in a sense, you know, the key idea for
that
search is like in the NFL, you want to go
deep.
Okay?
And, and, and try to find good solutions
quickly.
Okay, when does it prune?
It prunes as soon as you're reach a note
which who's evaluation is worth in the
best found solution.
Okay?
And one of the questions I have for you
is, how efficient is it from a memory
standpoint, okay?
And I'm going to always ask you questions
like this during this class, okay?
And the key anyone you want to answer them
is, you have to exaggerate, okay?
So, just assume, you know,
extreme cases and try to see all these
things are working, okay?
So, how much space, you know, is a branch
and bound, is that first branch and bound
going to take?
Okay, can you find, can you, can you find
the answer to that?
Well it's very simple, right?
.
You always go left, left, left until you
get stuck.
Okay?
So essentially the number of notes you can
accumulate in memory
of one time is essentially the length of
that particular branch,
which is this particular case is the
number of items you can put in an upside.
So yes, it's actually pretty memory
efficient because
you look at everyone of the item, you
have to do that because you have to find
out whether you select them or not.
And that's what you select inside a
particular branch.
Once you have, you know, explored that
branch you
can remove some of these notes, and you
would
select other ones by sticking the other
branches, but
you always have essentially one branch at
any one time.
Okay?
So, lets look at the next technique which
is best-first branch and bound.
And to illustrate this, I'm going to use a
very, very simple relaxation, the one
where we remove
the capacity constraint, because that
allows me to express,
you know, illustrate a concepts in a
better fashion.
Same, you know, same ratio of, you know,
values weight that done before.
Same capacity for nap sack.
Okay?
And once again all the notes, the values
that I've accumulated, the space left in
the knapsack and the optimistic
evaluation, okay.
So, initially best research, look at the
particular item, and then generate two
sub-problems, okay.
Whether you select the item or you don't
select the item, okay.
And now that first search, or best-first
search, is
going to look at all the notes which are
there, okay.
And select the one, okay, which is not
close.
Which means we haven't explored, you know,
its children yet.
Okay, which is the best evaluation?
And in this particular case, we take the
one where we selected
the item, and which has a value of 128,
right?
And we basically explore its, you know,
generate its two children, okay?
One of them is infeasible, and the other
one is a value 80, okay?
And now we basically have to consider
these three notes, one of which is
infeasible.
So we have essentially to consider these
two.
And we take the one which has the best
evaluation, which is this one.
Okay, we expand the children again, okay,
and what
we get now is these three notes, okay,
which have
evaluated tree and, and then 35.
And once again we take the one which has
the best evaluation, 83, okay, and we
expand it.
And we get a feasible solution there which
has
a pretty bad value of 48, and an
infeasible solution.
Okay, so at that point once again, you
know, we will be basically evaluating,
taking the best note, the note which has
the best evaluation for expansion, okay?
So it's going to, so this note we already
know,
but I'll come back to that in a moment.
We already
know that we would never select it right?
Because it's worth in the best solution
that we have,
but we expand this one and we find two
solutions.
One with value 80 and one with value 45.
Okay, and this is the best solution that
we have.
At this point we look at the best, you
know, note, which is not expanded inside a
tree.
We see this guy, but you see this guy
doesn't have to be expanded, which is
already worse than the best solution we
have, we have found so far, so we can stop
the exploration at that point.
Okay?
So that's best for search.
Okay.
You always look at the note which has the
best optimistic evaluation that is the one
that you select.
You expand, you know its children, and
then you repeat the process
select the one which is the best
evaluation and keep doing this, okay?
So, in a sense best-first search is always
greedy, right,
always go for the best, okay, and expand
that one, okay?
Most of the time when you expand that
particular note,
you know, they will, their value may go up
and therefore you
may go down and therefore you don't select
that many more, okay?
When is best-first search pruning?
It's essentially pruning when, you know,
you
tried all the nodes that you can expand
if a value which is worst than the best
solutions that you have found so far.
At that point, you have all these nodes
which are floating around.
They've not been expanded, okay, but it
makes no
sense to actually explore any of them, so
you stop.
And that's,
you know, when the computation stops.
Now, is it memory efficient?
Think about it, okay, once again.
Exaggerate.
Okay?
How would we be exaggerating in this
particular problem?
Okay?
Well we can be just city.
Right, suppose that, you know, the, the
optimistic evaluation is going to be
amazingly optimistic.
It's going to give you plus infinity all
the time.
So if you do that, how much space
are you going to use in best-first branch
and bound?
Think about it, okay?
Essentially what you going to do is, take
an oath.
They have all the same value, infinity.
You're going to expand one, okay?
And then you're going to expand the other
one, and so on.
And you will have to expand all of them.
So, you're going to store the entire tree
inside
memory, which is kind of a disaster,
right?
Because normally you will take exponential
time,
but you will also take exponential space.
And space is actually one of the main
limits in computers these days.
Okay, so,
you know, you know this is, this is the
worst case for you know a best-first
branch and bound.
Know you may ask, when is best-first
branch and bound really good?
Okay?
And once again, exaggerate, right?
And we can do the exact opposite
exaggeration, right?
So you have the perfect evaluation, okay?
If you have the perfect evaluation, okay,
then
you will select the minimal number of
notes.
Okay, so you see a little
bit about what's best for branch and
bound.
If the relaxation is really good, then,
the, the, what,
the number that you explore would be
little, will be,
you know, very small otherwise you, you
will explore a
large number of notes, and these notes are
inside memory.
Okay.
Now, let me talk about the last search
technique that
I want to talk about today, which is
limited discrepancy search.
It's actually a very interesting and
amazing heur-, you know search strategy.
And it assume
that you have a good heuristic, okay.
Assume that you have a greedy algorithm
which is really good, okay
and that it makes very few mistakes okay,
that's what the issue.
The heuristic is making very few mistakes
we assume that the search tree is
binary, okay, and following that heuristic
mean,
its always going left, left, left, left.
Right, so you select item, you select the
item, you select the item.
Okay, and branching right means the
heuristic is making a mistake.
Okay.
So if you do this, okay, this is what,
you know, limited discrepancy search does,
okay.
It wants to avoid mistake at all costs,
So we basically explore a search space by
increasing number of mistakes.
We first explore something which has, you
know, zero mistakes, one mistakes, two
mistakes.
Okay, and what we're doing there is really
trusting the heuristic lesson last.
Okay.
We start by trusting the heuristic, trying
to avoid mistakes, and then
allow a certain number of mistakes and
then more and more mistakes
until we don't trust the heuristic.
Okay.
So in a sense the way to view this is that
limited discrepancy search can be viewed
as a technique which is basically
exploring the
search, this entire tree, through a bunch
of waves.
The first waves assume that you make no
mistake.
The next wave, you know, wave number one,
assume that you can make one mistake.
And then wave number two, two mistakes,
and then so on and so forth.
Okay?
So let me show you that on
the exhaustive tree.
Okay?
So you start at the root of use tree, and
then you assume that you make no mistake.
You follow the heuristic all the time.
That means what?
Branching left, left, left, okay, and
that's what you see there.
This is, you know, the first wave that you
see there.
Okay.
Now the second wave is going to lower you
form one mistake.
Okay.
So that basically means that you can only
branch once, on the right.
Okay.
So for instance you can go here, okay, but
then you would have to go left,
left, left, left.
Okay, and this is what you see in the
first wave.
Okay, you go left, you go right and then
left, left, left, or you go left and
then one right and then only left or left,
left and then one right over here, right.
So this is what you explore in the second
wave,
and there is something which is really
interesting here, right?
So, this is half of the search space, this
is the second half of the search space.
And what you can see here is already, in
wave, in the second wave,
you are already exploring one particular
configuration, which
is in the second half of the search space.
Which depth first search would never do,
until, you know, it takes, it,
it, it has explored the entire first half
of the search space, right?
And this is one of the interesting things
about limited discrepancy search.
It actually probes the search space in
many different places.
Okay?
Then the third wave is going to be makes
two mistakes that makes, that means that
you can
take two rights and one left.
Okay, and that's what you see there.
And that point we have almost explored
everything.
Okay.
And then essentially the last web is
going to explore this guys on the left.
Okay, so let me show you this example of
the knapsack example as well.
Okay.
So we start from the configuration, okay,
in wave one, we start from the root.
And we branch left only, boom, boom, boom.
And in this particular case, it's kind
of annoying, because you get into
infeasibility
very quickly.
Okay?
The first wave, okay, is basically, you
can do one right.
And this is what you get, okay?
And, so you basically make one right
there, with, you,
you make a mistake for, you know, refer
back to the
heuristic, you let the heuristic make a
mistake, and then you
go left, or you go right, there, and go
left again.
And at that particular point, you find the
optimal solution already.
Okay?
And then in wave three, you explore two
mistakes for every one.
And most of these things are going to be
rejected, of course, because we have
already the optimal solution there, okay?
So, limited discrepancy search.
In summary, trust the greedy heuristic.
When does it prune?
Think about it.
Why, it's exactly like in that first
search.
When you see a note, okay, it does an
evaluation
which is worse than the best found
solution so far.
You know that you don't have to explore
it, so it prunes like in best-first
search.
And no, here is an interesting question,
okay?
Is it memory efficient?
Okay.
So, compared to depth-first and best-first
search, is it memory efficient?
Okay.
Now this is a very interesting question.
You know why?
Because I even told you really how to
implement this, okay.
And depending upon the way you would
implement this search, okay.
There will be an interesting trade off
between space and time, okay.
You can implement it very efficiently,
but it will take a lot of space.
Or you can implement it by doing redundant
work and it will take minimal space.
So the implementation can be between
the best-first and the depth-first search
approach.
Okay?
So think about it and think how you would
do this.
This is a very interesting topic.
Now limited discrepancy searches on
beautiful application is scheduling.
We'll come back to that and rounding as
well.
So it's a very interesting technique when
you have
a good heuristic, when you know what
you're doing.
Okay?
So,
let me conclude here.
So, we have seen search strategies here
and we have two class time about
relaxation.
Okay?
The big idea last time was relaxation.
The big idea today is search, okay.
Now how do you choose between them, okay.
This is a very interesting topic in
optimization.
This is one of the most important topic.
You can find really strong relaxation, but
they will be so slow that
you will explore a very small tree, but it
take a long time.
Or you can have a relaxation, which is
really strong.
The trees and a really fast computer.
And, the trees the size of your search
base substantially.
So, you have to find, you know the right
relaxation and
the right part of the search tree that you
will explore.
This is a very interesting topic.
Okay?
Most of this is going to be problem
specific like everything in optimization.
Okay?
And finally, you know, there are many
other strategies.
And, you know, I really encourage you to
actually think outside the box, and
think, if you can find all the kind of
strategies that are going to be good.
Okay?
Think about it, okay?
So, at this point, this is very
interesting.
We have covered, you know the knapsack
problem entirely.
Okay.
It's time for you to start the
assignments, okay, and we'll
go into more sophisticated techniques in
the next couple of lectures.
Thank you very much guys.
Okay, so it's time to actually go to work
and actually solve these assignments.
Bye.